<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Enoch's translation, in a sermon preached at the funerals of the Right Honourable Thomas Earl of Elgin, Baron of Whorlton, &amp;c. In the parish-church of Malden in Bedford-shire, Decemb. 31. 1663. By Rich. Pearson D.D.</title>
            <author>Pearson, Richard, Chaplain to the Earl of Elgin.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1664</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 50 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 19 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A53903</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P1012</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R216919</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99828633</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99828633</idno>
            <idno type="VID">33064</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A53903)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 33064)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1956:8)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Enoch's translation, in a sermon preached at the funerals of the Right Honourable Thomas Earl of Elgin, Baron of Whorlton, &amp;c. In the parish-church of Malden in Bedford-shire, Decemb. 31. 1663. By Rich. Pearson D.D.</title>
                  <author>Pearson, Richard, Chaplain to the Earl of Elgin.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 32 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by James Flesher for Thomas Clark, at the South Entrance of the Royal-Exchange,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1664.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Title page inlaid; other leaves apparently repaired.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Elgin, Thomas Bruce, --  Earl of, 1599-1663 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Hebrews II, 5 --  Sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Funeral sermons --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:33064:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:33064:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>ENOCH</hi>'s TRANSLATION, IN A SERMON PREACHED At the Funerals of the Right Honourable THOMAS Earl of <hi>ELGIN,</hi> Baron of <hi>WHORLTON,</hi> &amp;c. In the Pariſh-Church of <hi>Malden</hi> in <hi>Bedford-ſhire, Decemb.</hi> 31. 1663.</p>
            <p>By RICH. PEARSON D. D.</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>recumbent skeleton with crossbones</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>James Fleſher</hi> for <hi>Thomas Clark,</hi> at the South-Entrance of the <hi>Royal Exchange.</hi> 1664.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <pb facs="tcp:33064:2"/>
            <p>Imprimatur.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>JOH. HALL, R. P. D. Epiſc.</hi> Lond. <hi>à Sac. Domeſt.</hi>
               </signed>
               <dateline>
                  <date>Feb. 22. 1663.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:33064:2"/>
            <head>To the Right Honourable, <hi>ROBERT</hi> Earl of <hi>Elgin,</hi> Baron of <hi>Whorlton,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Right Honourable,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N the Robe of <hi>Aaron</hi>'s Ephod, by God's appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, there was to be <hi>a Bell and a Pomegra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Ex. 28. 34.</note> 
               <hi>A Bell and a Pomegranate, round about the hem of the Robe.</hi> Why the Bells were not placed aloft, but <hi>in Extremis,</hi> in the Hem or Skirts of the Robe, <hi>Origen</hi> gives this Moral account, <hi>Ut de extremis</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Hom. 9. in <hi>Exod.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>nunquam ſileas, ſemper ſones,</hi> To put men in mind of their latter End; that even from <hi>Aaron</hi>'s Garment the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of Mortality might be always ſounding in the ears of the People. Every Funeral Sermon is as a Paſsing-peal from theſe Bells of <hi>Aaron.</hi> In this there is not onely the Bell of <hi>Aaron,</hi> but the Pomegranate, the fruit of a Holy and Pious Life, expreſt in the rare Example of your ever-Honoured <hi>Father.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is true of the Lives of the Saints what one ſaid of the Pomegranate, that there is in the beſt <hi>aliquod granum putre,</hi> ſome one grane or other amiſs. Yet I am perſwaded
<pb facs="tcp:33064:3"/> there were in him as few faulty granes, and as great Emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nencies of ſolid Vertue and Piety, as in any perſon whom this Age hath produced. He hath derived to Your Honour a moſt compendious way of Excelling, in leaving You both an high advantage of Doing Good, by an honourable Fortune, and a great Example of Being Good, by beating out the way be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore You.</p>
            <p>And by the bleſsing of God Your Lordſhip will exceed the Copy, having already given to the world the ſignal evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dences of Your great Love to Religion and Loyalty, the ſurest Foundation of all Chriſtian and Heroick Vertues. Which that they may be increaſed and multiplied, with all other Bleſsings, upon Your Lordſhip and Your Noble Family, ſhall be my conſtant and earneſt prayer.</p>
            <p>In the mean time Your Lordſhip will be pleaſed to accept of this ſhort and imperfect Draught, adventured into the publick view in pure obedience to Your Lordſhip's Deſires, which have the force of undiſputable Commands upon</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Honour's moſt humble Servant and Chaplain, RICH. PEARSON.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:33064:3"/>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>HEB. 11. 5.</bibl>
               <q>By Faith Enoch was tranſlated, that he ſhould not ſee death, and was not found, becauſe God had tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlated him: for before his tranſlation he had this teſtimony, that he pleaſed God.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HIS whole Chapter is as a gol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den Kalendar, a ſacred Roll, containing the Lives of the ancient and holy Patriarchs, and the famous acts of thoſe Hero's which were the Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thies, not of <hi>David,</hi> but of Heaven; the men of Renown which were before the times of Chriſt. And particularly this verſe preſents us with an excellent Panegyrick of the renowned Patriarch <hi>Enoch,</hi> the ſeventh from <hi>Adam,</hi> the great Prophet of the Firſt world, whoſe Prophetical eye was ſo illuminated, that it could reach from one end of the world to the other; and living ſo near to
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:33064:4"/> the beginning of the World, foretold the diſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution and conſummation of it. In this Text we have the Panegyrick of this noble Patriarch: it conſiſts of many clauſes; but if we marſhal them into a Logical method, we may reduce them to theſe three heads<hi>:</hi>
            </p>
            <l>His Converſation in the world.</l>
            <l>His Removal out of the world. And</l>
            <l>The mutual Correſpondence of both theſe.</l>
            <p>His Converſation in the world, that is expreſt in the firſt and laſt words of the Text, He walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>by Faith,</hi> and <hi>He pleaſed God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>His Removal out of the world, that is expreſt in the middle clauſes, He <hi>was tranſlated, that he ſhould not ſee death, and</hi> he <hi>was not found, becauſe God had tranſlated him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The mutual Correſpondence of theſe two, that lies in the Dependance and Connexion of the words. <hi>By Faith</hi> he <hi>was tranſlated,</hi> in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the verſe. Piety is a comfortable prepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive to a happy tranſlation. And in the latter end of the verſe, <hi>God tranſlated him,</hi> for <hi>he pleaſed God.</hi> A bleſſed tranſlation is an infallible conſequent of a holy and heavenly life. Theſe are the ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral parts of the Text, of which I intend to ſpeak.</p>
            <p>I begin with the Firſt, The holy Converſation <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> of the Patriarch <hi>Enoch</hi> whilſt he was in the
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:33064:4"/> world, deſcribed both by the Principle of a holy life, that is Faith, <hi>By faith Enoch,</hi> in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the verſe; and by the Conſequence or Reſult of it, in the latter end of the verſe, He <hi>pleaſed God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The firſt part of this Elogium is drawn from the Principle or foundation of a godly life, that is Faith. It is the motto which S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſets in the front of all that was praiſe-worthy in the Saints, as the top of their commendation: <hi>By faith Abel</hi> did thus and thus, <hi>By faith Abraham, By faith Moſes,</hi> and <hi>By faith Enoch.</hi> This is as the Title-page to all of them. Even the Saints be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Chriſt had the grace of Faith for their lamp, as well as thoſe that followed after; and by that Faith they lived and walked in their ſeveral ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions: and it was a Faith not different from ours in Kind; their Faith and ours were the ſame in ſubſtance, and were both fixed upon the ſame Object: the difference was onely Gradual and cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtantial; they believed in that which was to be accompliſhed, and we in that which is already accompliſhed. Their Faith look'd for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, and their voice was that of the Pſalmiſt, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 116. 10. <hi>Credidi, propter quod loquar, I believed, therefore will I ſpeak:</hi> Our Faith looks backward to Chriſt already exhibited, and our voice is that
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:33064:5"/> of S. <hi>Paul,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4. 13. <hi>I believed, therefore have I ſpoken.</hi> So in the ſubſtance of Salvation they ſhared with us, and we with them: they Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers as well as we, they Chriſtians as well as we; <hi>Chriſtiani ante Chriſtum,</hi> as <hi>Tertullian</hi> ſpeaks, Chriſtians even before Chriſt was come into the world: and as we believing receive Redemption by the Bloud of Chriſt actually ſhed; ſo they al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo believing received Redemption by the ſame Bloud of Chriſt which was virtually ſhed even from the beginning of the world. So they and we make up one Church, one Spiritual Build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>built upon the foundation of the Apoſtles and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, Jeſus Chriſt himſelf being the chief corner-ſtone,</hi> Eph. 2. 20.</p>
            <p>Again, it is farther obſervable, that of all the Excellencies for which the Saints are extolled in Scripture, above all they are magnified for their Faith. In every of theſe examples that are men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned in this Chapter, Faith as it is the firſt, ſo it is the principal part of their commendation. There were other Eminencies which were re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable in them, <hi>Abel</hi>'s Innocency, <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Obedience, <hi>Moſes</hi>'s Zeal, <hi>Noah</hi>'s Righteouſneſs, <hi>Enoch</hi>'s Devotion: but the high approbation which the Spirit of God gives them is for their Faith, as the firſt and leading Grace, as the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:33064:5"/> and fundamental Grace, which is the root and ſpring of all the reſt; as that Grace which made them live Religiouſly here, <hi>By faith Enoch pleaſed God;</hi> and as that Grace which carried them to Heaven afterwards, <hi>By faith Enoch was tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlated.</hi> This order of Salvation God hath ſet; No coming to Heaven but by Chriſt, no com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to Chriſt but by Faith: So No Faith no Chriſt, and no Chriſt no Salvation. Whereas ſome have vainly thought to make Saints of the old Philoſophers, as if by the right uſe of Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, or by the improvement of their natural En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowments they could attain Salvation: this fond charity of theirs is much like that legendary de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion of Pope <hi>Gregory,</hi> who is ſaid by his prayers to have fetch'd the Soul of the Emperour <hi>Trajan</hi> out of Hell, being moved with compaſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on for the juſtice which he had once done to a poor widow. But the ſtory tells us that by reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation he received this anſwer, That however he was heard in that Petition, yet <hi>Caveret in poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum,</hi> he ſhould beware hereafter that he did not preſume to pray for any that was dead unbap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized. It is an equal preſumption in theſe men to think by their opinion to redeem from Hell the Souls of thoſe Heathens who lived and died without Faith, without Chriſt, and without
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:33064:6"/> God in the world. An opinion not unlike to that of the <hi>Turks</hi> in their <hi>Alcoran,</hi> That every man ſhall be ſaved in his own Religion, be it what it will, if he be but devout in it. Briefly, it is an opinion which overturns the whole frame of revealed Truth, that any man can be ſaved without Chriſt, or have any intereſt in Chriſt without Faith. This is the reaſon why the Apoſtle in this Chapter makes ſuch frequent mention of Faith in the behalf of all the Saints, as the Grace which carried them to Heaven, as the Grace which God eſteems and approves above all, as the radi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal and fundamental Grace which is the Root and Principle of a vertuous and holy life. <hi>By faith Enoch;</hi> that's the firſt Elogium, in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the verſe.</p>
            <p>The ſecond is drawn from the Conſequence or Reſult of it, in the cloſe of the verſe, He <hi>pleaſed God.</hi> This follows naturally upon the former, as the Effect upon the Cauſe. For as the Apoſtle has laid down the Maxim, in the next verſe, <hi>Without Faith it is impoſsible to pleaſe God:</hi> ſo with Faith it is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible not to pleaſe him. Faith is the Grace that incorporates us into Chriſt: being incorporate into Chriſt we are made partakers of all his Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits; his Satisfaction becomes ours, his Obedience ours, his Righteouſneſs ours: being thus cloth'd
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:33064:6"/> in the robe of his Righteouſneſs put on by Faith, we become accepted of God, and God well pleaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with us. Again, Faith is the Root from whence infallibly ſprings the Fruit of a Holy and Godly life; and with ſuch Fruit God is well pleaſed.</p>
            <p>But the Apoſtle here ſets it down with ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage: It is not barely, He <hi>pleaſed God,</hi> but <hi>He had this teſtimony, that he pleaſed God.</hi> And from whom had he this teſtimony? even from God himſelf. We find it given unto him by the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of God, <hi>Gen.</hi> 5. 24. there it is ſaid, <hi>Enoch walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with God,</hi> and here, <hi>Enoch pleaſed God.</hi> To <hi>walk with God</hi> and to <hi>pleaſe God</hi> are phraſes equivalent. <hi>Can two walk together,</hi> ſaith the Prophet, <hi>unleſs they be agreed?</hi> that is, unleſs they be pleaſed; <hi>Amos</hi> 3. 3. Therefore the Apoſtle S. <hi>Paul</hi> joyns theſe two words together in 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 4. 1. <hi>Ye have received of us how ye ought to walk, and to pleaſe God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Would you then know what it is to <hi>pleaſe God?</hi> S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> leads us to the beginning of this duty: <hi>Placere Deo incipit qui in ſe odit quod Deo diſplicet;</hi> Then we begin to pleaſe God, when we hate and abhor in our ſelves whatſoever is diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſing unto him. S. <hi>Baſil</hi> carries us further; <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Then we pleaſe <note place="margin">Baſ. <hi>l. de Virgin.</hi>
               </note> God, when by a holy and a vertuous life we en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to <hi>make our ſelves like unto God.</hi> More
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:33064:7"/> particularly, To pleaſe God is, to love him, to fear him, to ſerve him, to praiſe him, to doe all thoſe things which are pleaſing and acceptable unto him.</p>
            <p>The reaſon is, God is the onely infinite good, and cannot take pleaſure in any thing but him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, or ſomething of himſelf. He is pleaſed with his Son, becauſe he is Himſelf; he is pleaſed with Piety, becauſe it is a beam of Himſelf wrought by his Spirit in the creature. So every action, the more it has of God, the more pleaſing it is unto him; and the more it has of Chriſt, the more it has of God; and the more it has of Faith, the more it has of Chriſt; and of all other Graces Faith is moſt pleaſing to him, becauſe it holds moſt of Chriſt: the more of Chriſt, the more acceptation we find with God, becauſe in him God is perfectly well pleaſed.</p>
            <p>The ſumme is this, The pleaſing of God muſt be both our Final cauſe, we muſt make it our End whilſt we are in the world, to direct all our actions to the Glory of God, to doe that which may pleaſe him; and our For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal cauſe, we muſt make it our Rule, it is the ſureſt Rule we can walk by, to doe thoſe things which are pleaſing unto God.</p>
            <p>Chriſt himſelf walked by this Rule, <hi>It is my</hi>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:33064:7"/> 
               <hi>meat and drink to doe my Father's will,</hi> Joh. 4. 34. <hi>David</hi> deſired to walk by this Rule, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 143. 10. <hi>O teach me to doe the thing that pleaſeth thee. Enoch</hi> went by this Rule, he <hi>walked by Faith,</hi> and he <hi>pleaſed God.</hi> And this is the Rule which is ſet to every Chriſtian, that Golden and unerring Rule, which can never deceive us, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 3. 22. to <hi>doe thoſe things which are pleaſing in his ſight.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So it excludes three falſe Rules, by which moſt men are wont to be over-ruled in the managing of their converſation.</p>
            <p>The firſt is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Self-pleaſing;</hi> that's a falſe Rule: we muſt not be <hi>ſelf-pleaſers, Rom.</hi> 15. 1. not to lean to our own Underſtandings, not to be ſwaied by our own Wills, not to be ruled by our own unruly Affections. <hi>I came not,</hi> ſaith Chriſt, <hi>to doe my own will, but the will of him that ſent me,</hi> Joh. 6. 38. That man is the beſt Servant of God who is leaſt his own Maſter, who knows no other <hi>velle</hi> and <hi>nolle,</hi> but onely to doe the will and pleaſure of God.</p>
            <p>The ſecond is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>the pleaſing of men;</hi> that is alſo a falſe Rule: the Apoſtle cries it down in <hi>Eph.</hi> 6. 6. <hi>Not as men-pleaſers, but as the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants of God.</hi> It is hard to be both a Servant of God and a Pleaſer of men; therefore the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle puts them as contradiſtinct and inconſiſtent
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:33064:8"/> deſignes, and if we will cleave to the one, we muſt renounce the other; 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2. 4. <hi>So ſpeak,</hi> ſo doe, <hi>not as pleaſing men, but God.</hi> The tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rizing Hypocrite does all to be ſeen of men, ſo ſpeaks as hunting after the Favour and Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plauſe and Approbation of men, with thoſe ſawning Prophets mentioned in <hi>Iſa.</hi> 30. 10. which <hi>ſpeak ſmooth things,</hi> and <hi>propheſie deceits. The Prophets propheſie falſly,</hi> and what's the reaſon? the <hi>people love to have it ſo,</hi> Jer. 5. 31. He that would approve himſelf a faithful Servant of God, muſt not look aſquint upon the Applauſe of men. S. <hi>Paul</hi> concludes for himſelf, and it may be a Rule for us, <hi>Gal.</hi> 1. 10. <hi>If I ſhould yet pleaſe men, I were not the ſervant of Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The third is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. If we muſt not pleaſe <hi>our ſelves,</hi> if we muſt not pleaſe <hi>men,</hi> much leſs <hi>Satan,</hi> who is God's adverſary. Whatſoever pleaſeth him is diſpleaſing to God. Then we pleaſe him, when we liſten to his ſuggeſtions, when we commit ſin, and delight to continue in it. As the good Angels rejoyce at our Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion, ſo our Sin and Confuſion is the pleaſure and paſtime of Satan. If we make it our End and our Rule (as we ought to doe) to pleaſe God, all theſe ways are to be abandoned.</p>
            <p>Here then was the high commendation of
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:33064:8"/> 
               <hi>Enoch</hi>'s Piety, he ſo lived, and ſo behaved him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf in the time of his pilgrimage, that by the teſtimony of God himſelf, he <hi>pleaſed God.</hi> It was a high Character, eſpecially from the mouth of God, and that recorded by the finger of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of God in the Book of God, <hi>in perpetuam rei memoriam.</hi> What an honour was it to <hi>Apelles</hi> to be enrolled among the Nobles of the New Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament, with this ſingular Elogium or Title of honour, <hi>Apelles approved in Chriſt?</hi> What an ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour to <hi>Moſes</hi> in the Old Teſtament to be called <note place="margin">Ro. 16. 10.</note> 
               <hi>the Servant of God?</hi> to <hi>Abraham,</hi> to be ſtyled <hi>the Friend of God?</hi> to <hi>David,</hi> to be called <hi>A man after God's own heart?</hi> All theſe concur in this honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Elogium given to the Patriarch <hi>Enoch</hi> in this Scripture, <hi>He had this teſtimony, that he pleaſed God.</hi> And thus much ſhall ſuffice for the firſt part of the Text, His pious Converſation whilſt he was in the world.</p>
            <p>Being ſuch an one, it was not fit that he ſhould make too long a ſtay in this world, which was not worthy of him. He was all this while a Candidate for Heaven, and having re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived God's approbation, thither God removes him: and by a ſpecial privilege he takes the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree of a glorified Saint, as it were <hi>per ſaltum,</hi> leaping over the threſhold of Death.</p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:33064:9"/>
            <p> This we have more particularly deſcribed un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> us in the Second part of the Text, which tells us of his honourable Removal out of the world, in theſe words, He <hi>was tranſlated, that he ſhould not ſee death, and was not found, becauſe God had tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlated him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Concerning this Tranſlation of <hi>Enoch</hi> many Queſtions have been ſtarted, but by the help of this Scripture we may be able to reſolve the moſt of them.</p>
            <p>One is, Whether <hi>Enoch</hi> was ſo tranſlated, that, as a perſon privileged from the law of Morta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, he died not. The Scruple is grounded up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on two ſeveral phraſes which are uſed by <hi>Moſes</hi> in the ſtory of <hi>Enoch, Gen.</hi> 5. 24.</p>
            <p>Firſt, in that it is ſaid <hi>God took him.</hi> Now this phraſe of <hi>taking away</hi> is uſed in Scripture to ſet forth the bleſſed Departure of the Saints out of this world by the ordinary way of Diſſolution. Thus, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 57. 1. <hi>Merciful men are taken away,</hi> that is, they die; and <hi>Job</hi> 32. 22. <hi>my Maker would ſoon take me away,</hi> that is, he would take away my Life, he would kill me.</p>
            <p>Again, it is ſaid in the ſame Scripture, that <hi>Enoch was not:</hi> and this alſo is a phraſe by which the Scripture ſometimes points out the ſtate of Death. So <hi>Gen.</hi> 42. 36. <hi>Joſeph is not, and Simeon</hi>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:33064:9"/> 
               <hi>is not,</hi> that is, they are both dead; for ſo <hi>Jacob</hi> at that time ſuppoſed them to be.</p>
            <p>But this Queſtion is clearly reſolved by S. <hi>Paul</hi> in this Scripture, where he tells us plainly, <hi>Enoch was tranſlated, that he ſhould not ſee death.</hi> That he ſhould not ſee death, that is, that he ſhould not die. It is like that other phraſe, <hi>Luk.</hi> 9. 27. <hi>There be ſome here that ſhall not taſte of death.</hi> To <hi>ſee death</hi> and to <hi>taſte of death</hi> are phraſes borrowed from two diſtinct Senſes, but have both the ſame ſignification: that is, ſaith S. <hi>Auguſtin, Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem non experietur,</hi> he ſhall have no experience of death. <hi>Enoch</hi> was ſo far exempted from the law of Death, that he did not ſo much as <hi>Taſte</hi> it, <hi>nè primoribus quidem labiis;</hi> ſo far privileged, that he did not ſo much as <hi>See</hi> it, <hi>nè primoribus quidem oculis.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So his <hi>Taking away</hi> was not a Taking away of Diſſolution, which implies Mortality; but a Taking away of Tranſlation, which prevents Death. Therefore we may obſerve, that in <hi>Gen.</hi> 5. where the Lives of the Patriarchs are record<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, of all the reſt who are mentioned both be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore and after <hi>Enoch,</hi> it runs thus, <hi>Seth lived</hi> ſo many <hi>years, and he died; Methuſelah</hi> ſo many <hi>years, and he died:</hi> but of <hi>Enoch</hi> otherwiſe, he <hi>lived</hi> ſo many <hi>years,</hi> and not ſaid, <hi>He died;</hi> but, to ſhew
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:33064:10"/> that he was a privileged perſon, <hi>Moſes</hi> gives him a ſingular and privilegiate expreſſion, <hi>God took him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Again, whereas it is there further expreſs'd, <hi>He was not,</hi> if we take the phraſe in its full ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gour, it ſignifies an abſolute Nullity, or Anni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hilation; but here it is ſo far from intending an Annihilation, that it does not betoken ſo much as an ordinary Extinction by Death. It is true, that as the Latines were wont to expreſs Death by the word <hi>Fuit,</hi> ſo the Hebrews by a <hi>Non fuit;</hi> but in this place it does not ſignifie ſo much, Therefore S. <hi>Paul</hi> in this Text mollifies the phraſe by a word of ſupply, <hi>Non fuit, He was not,</hi> that is, <hi>Non fuit inventus,</hi> He was not Found; He was not any more in a viſible communion with men; He was ſecretly tranſlated by God, as <hi>Moſes</hi> ſecretly buried by God: It was not known what was become of him, till God re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed it. We ſee other men when they go out of the world: Even <hi>Elias</hi> himſelf was ſeen by <hi>Eliſha</hi> when he aſcended. But none of the Patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>archs ſaw <hi>Enoch</hi> go; and being gone, he was not to be found. The ſons of the Prophets might ſearch and ſeek for him, as they did for <hi>Elias,</hi> but not meet with him. Again, as it was a Secret, ſo a Total Tranſlation, both in Soul and Body.
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:33064:10"/> Other Saints, though their Souls be carried up on the wings of Angels, as <hi>Lazarus</hi> was, yet their Bodies are to be found, they remain behind, and are laid aſleep in their graves, as S. <hi>Peter</hi> ſpeaks of the Patriarch <hi>David, Act.</hi> 2. 29. <hi>He is both dead and buried, and his ſepulchre is with us unto this day. Enoch</hi> was not to be found either way: in him there was no Separation of Soul and Body by death, but a total Tranſlation of both.</p>
            <p>That for the firſt Queſtion.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Some will grant that <hi>Enoch</hi> died not, he was not then <hi>Mortuus,</hi> but make a queſtion whether he was not <hi>Aliquando moriturus,</hi> after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards to die, namely towards the end of the World, having preached Repentance to the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles; for ſo they reade that place in <hi>Eccleſiaſtic.</hi> 44. 16. <hi>Tranſlatus eſt in paradiſum, ut det gentibus poe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitentiam:</hi> Our Tranſlation better, <hi>He was tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlated, being an example of repentance to all genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</hi> The more probable ground of this opinion is fetch'd from the common law of Mortality, by which it is appointed for all men once to die: <hi>Pſal.</hi> 89. 48. <hi>What man is he that lives, and ſhall not ſee death?</hi> But the Apoſtle in this place reſolves alſo this Queſtion, that <hi>Enoch</hi>'s privilege did not conſiſt in a bare reprieve, or a deferring of Death till ſome further time; then it had been
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:33064:11"/> enough for the Apoſtle to have ſaid, <hi>Et non vidit mortem,</hi> he did not ſee death: but it conſiſted in a final preſervation and exemption from it; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is expreſs'd more fully, <hi>he was tranſlated, ut non videret mortem, that he ſhould not,</hi> that is, <hi>that he ſhould never ſee death.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And for that general law of Mortality, it is not a Rule ſo peremptory but that it admits of ſome exception. S. <hi>Paul</hi> tells us of thoſe Saints who ſhall be found alive at Chriſt's coming to Judgment, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. 52. <hi>We ſhall not all ſleep,</hi> that is, we ſhall not all die, <hi>but we ſhall be changed, in a moment,</hi> &amp;c. That Change is not properly Death, but an equivalent or analogical Death. So <hi>Enoch</hi> here, though he might admit of ſome ſuch momentany Death, in the change of a corru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptible Body into an incorruptible, yet there was no Separation, and therefore, properly ſpeaking, he was free from Death.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, there's yet a further Queſtion con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Place of <hi>Enoch</hi>'s Tranſlation, whither it was that God removed him. Some will have it to be into a Terreſtrial Paradiſe, the very ſame out of which <hi>Adam</hi> was ejected, a place free from all thoſe corporal moleſtations and inconve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niences which attend upon us in our earthly pilgrimage; but withall a place which does not
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:33064:11"/> afford the viſion of God, or the happineſs of a Comprehendour. This Opinion is grounded upon the fore-named place of the Son of <hi>Sirach, Eccleſiaſt.</hi> 44. 16. where <hi>Enoch</hi> is ſaid to be <hi>tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlated into Paradiſe.</hi> But this will appear to be a very weak and a ſandy foundation: For beſides that the Author is Apocryphal, the Text is fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſified, the word <hi>Paradiſe</hi> being foiſted into the vulgar Latin, which is not in the Greek; and a corrupt Gloſs inferr'd upon it, <hi>Into Paradiſe,</hi> therefore <hi>into an Earthly Paradiſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But the Apoſtle in this Scripture reſolves al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo this Queſtion, where it is ſaid that <hi>God tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlated him;</hi> and recorded as a great privilege, Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe <hi>he pleaſed God,</hi> therefore God tranſlated him. If onely into an Earthly Paradiſe to be there confined, it had not been a Gain, but a Loſs; not a Prerogative, but a Prejudice; not a Privilege, but a Puniſhment: that whereas the Souls of the other Saints after the ending of a ſhort Pilgrimage upon Earth are immediately carried up to thoſe Celeſtial manſions, where they do enjoy the viſion of God, the ſociety of Saints and Angels, and are <hi>for ever bleſſed with the Lord;</hi> yet <hi>Enoch,</hi> an eminent Saint, who <hi>had this</hi> ſingular <hi>teſtimony</hi> from God's own mouth, <hi>that he pleaſed God,</hi> ſhould be the onely perſon con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn'd
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:33064:12"/> to an Earthly Paradiſe for ages and ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerations, and ſo long kept out of Heaven, even almoſt from the beginning to the end of the world.</p>
            <p>The truth is, this Opinion of <hi>Enoch</hi>'s Tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion into an Earthly Paradiſe is a wild conceit, without either ground of Reaſon or authority of Scripture: and the ancient Fathers, ſpeaking of <hi>Enoch</hi> and <hi>Elias,</hi> (whatſoever they ſay of the degrees of Glory) determine of both, that they were taken up into the place of Glory. He is there, ſaith <hi>Epiphanius,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>in a body</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Epiph. <hi>haer.</hi> 64.</note> 
               <hi>ſpiritualized.</hi> He doth <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ſo S. <hi>Baſil Seleuc. converſe with Angels.</hi> He was car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried, <note place="margin">Baſ. <hi>Sel. Or.</hi> 11. <hi>Id. Orat.</hi> 40</note> ſaith the ſame Father, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>above all the bounds of</hi> viſible <hi>nature:</hi> whither can that be but into Heaven? Whence <hi>Iſid. Peluſ.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Iſid. Peluſ. l. 2. <hi>ep.</hi> 37.</note> calls <hi>Elias</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>coelipetam Eliam,</hi> one that reach'd Heaven corporally. The ſame may be ſaid of <hi>Enoch.</hi> Of all the Saints theſe were the onely Royal pare who had the honour of this privilege. All the other Saints at the time of their diſſolution are taken up in their Souls, their Bodies are not tranſlated thither untill the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Reſurrection. S. <hi>Paul</hi> and S. <hi>John</hi> were taken up in ſpirit, by viſion or ex<gap reason="illegible" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ſie; but <hi>Enoch</hi> in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon. So it might have a two-fold reference.</p>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:33064:12"/>
            <p> 1. It was a fore-runner of the Aſcenſion of Chriſt. Chriſt had fore-runners of all the other paſſages of his Incarnation. The <hi>Baptiſt</hi> was a fore-runner of his Birth; <hi>John</hi> born of the barren womb, Chriſt of the Virgin: a fore-runner of his Death; <hi>Iſaac,</hi> the onely ſon of his father, bound upon the Altar, as Chriſt nail'd upon the Croſs: a fore-runner of his Reſurrection; <hi>Jonas</hi> after three days brought forth out of the belly of the Whale, by the power of God, as Chriſt by his own power raiſed out of the bowels of the earth: and a fore-runner alſo of his Aſcenſion; <hi>Enoch</hi> tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlated into Heaven, as Chriſt himſelf was after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards.</p>
            <p>2<hi rend="sup">ly</hi>, It was a fore-runner of our rapture at the Laſt day; to aſſure us, that the weight of our Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies ſhall be no impediment of our Aſſumption into Heaven: that as God gave us pledges of our Reſurrection in both Teſtaments, in the Old, by ſuch as were raiſed by the Prophets; in the New, by ſuch as Chriſt himſelf raiſed; ſo he hath not left us without remarkable pledges of our Aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion into Heaven. In every ſtate of the world there was one that was taken up; <hi>Enoch</hi> before the Law, <hi>Elias</hi> under the Law, <hi>Chriſt</hi> after the Law: that in all Ages the Saints might have ſome pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ambles of everlaſting Life. For this reaſon <hi>Epipha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius</hi>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:33064:13"/> calls <hi>Enoch the Firſt-begotten of the Reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on;</hi> and S. <hi>Gregory, Aſcenſionis praenuncium, the Fore-runner of our Aſcenſion.</hi> What was wrought upon him in the firſt Age of the world, is daily wrought upon the Saints in all Ages of the world; in reſpect of their Souls, at the time of their departure they are tranſlated and taken up into Heaven; and at the Laſt day it ſhall be wrought upon the Bodies of all the Saints, when they <hi>ſhall be caught up into the clouds,</hi> and <hi>meet the Lord in the air,</hi> and ſo <hi>ſhall ever be with the Lord.</hi> I have done with the Second Part of the Text, His honourable Removal out of the world.</p>
            <p>The Third and laſt is, The mutual Correſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence between the two former Parts, his Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> and his Tranſlation. His holy Converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion that was a comfortable preparative of his happy Tranſlation, <hi>By faith Enoch was tranſlated,</hi> in the beginning of the verſe<hi>:</hi> and his happy Tranſlation that was a neceſſary conſequent of his holy and pious Converſation, in the latter end of the verſe, <hi>God tranſlated him,</hi> becauſe <hi>before his tranſlation he pleaſed God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>From hence will ariſe theſe two Propoſitions, whereof the one will ſerve to guide and direct, the other to comfort and eſtabliſh us in our way to Heaven.</p>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:33064:13"/>
            <p> The firſt is this, That a holy Converſation is a ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary preparative to a happy Tranſlation. There's no paſſing into that Temple of Honour, but by this of Vertue. We muſt <hi>enter through the Gates into the City, Rev.</hi> 22. 14. The City is Heaven, and Grace is the Gate that leads into it. You have it expounded in the former part of that verſe, <hi>Bleſſed are they that doe his commandments, that they may have right to the Tree of life.</hi> Heaven is a holy place, <hi>no unclean thing ſhall enter</hi> there, <hi>nor whatſoever defileth, nor whatſoever worketh abomination:</hi> It is a Heavenly place, the earthly and covetous worldling ſhall not enter there. To ſuch a man the door of Heaven is as <hi>the eye of a Needle,</hi> and ſuch a man is to it as a <hi>Camel;</hi> if he would thred this Needle, he muſt take away this Bunch from off his back, caſt away the love of worldly Riches. Heaven is the habitation of Righteouſneſs, no unjuſt perſon ſhall enter there, <hi>nor thieves, nor covetous, nor extortioners,</hi> nor oppreſſors, nor grinders of the face of the poor. It is God's <hi>holy Hill,</hi> and <hi>David</hi> tells us by what ſteps we muſt aſcend unto it, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 15. and <hi>Pſal.</hi> 24. by <hi>walking uprightly,</hi> and <hi>working righteouſneſs,</hi> and <hi>ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the truth,</hi> by <hi>cleanneſs of hands</hi> and <hi>purity of heart.</hi> Such an one <hi>ſhall receive bleſsing from the Lord, and righteouſneſs from the God of his Salvation.</hi> In a word; would you hope for a comfortable tranſlation at
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:33064:14"/> the hour of death? you muſt learn to live the life of Faith; <hi>By faith Enoch was tranſlated:</hi> learn ſo to or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der your lives as may be well-pleaſing and acce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptable unto God; <hi>Enoch was tranſlated,</hi> becauſe <hi>he pleaſed God.</hi> That's the firſt Propoſition, A holy Converſation is a neceſſary preparative of a happy Tranſlation.</p>
            <p>And the ſecond is like unto it, That a happy Tranſlation is an infallible conſequent of a holy and godly Converſation. S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> lays it down for an undeniable truth, <hi>Non poteſt malè mori qui be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne vixerit,</hi> No man can die ill that lives well; be it a ſudden, a violent, a painful, a bloudy death, yet he is happy in it, becauſe He cannot die ill that lives well. Let us make ſure of this <hi>viaticum,</hi> Faith working by Love, and all will be well. He that has often uſed to walk with God, as <hi>Enoch</hi> did, that has made it his care and conſcience to pleaſe God, has this Praeludium of a happy Diſſolution, he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins in Grace, and he muſt needs end in Glory.</p>
            <p>In a word, Let us make this uſe of <hi>Enoch</hi>'s Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlation, often to look up to that place whither he was taken. Had Earth been <hi>Enoch</hi>'s home, had this World been his abiding City, God would never have taken him from hence: but being a pilgrim here, he takes him away. And however we have no hope of this privilege whilſt we are in our mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:33064:14"/> Pilgrimage, to be immediately taken up in the Body, as he was; yet we muſt aſpire thither in our Affections and Deſires. That is a thing we may reach unto, and Nature it ſelf will help us with ſome directions to it, having given Man an erect Stature and a ſublime Countenance, that he may behold his Heavenly Original, and often meditate on the place from whence he came, that is Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven; that he may have a Heavenly Converſation, ſutable to the place whither he is deſigned to go, that's Heaven. But the Scripture gives us better di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections, to look up thither with the Eye of Faith; that will carry us further then the eye of the Body, not onely to the Starry Heaven, but to the Beatifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal, where our Hope is, where our Country is, where the Saints and Angels are, where Chriſt himſelf is. If there be any love of Chriſt, we will be often travelling thither, he is gone before; if any love of the Saints, they are gone before; if any love of Happineſs, we cannot hope to find it here, it is in Heaven, or no where. Let us lift up our hearts thither, there let us fix our eyes, thither let us bend our courſe, and ſo order our Converſation in this world, that we may be fit for a better: that when the time of our Diſſolution is come, we may hope for a bleſſed Tranſlation, having walked by Faith, and laboured to pleaſe God, as <hi>Enoch</hi> did; <hi>By Faith Enoch,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:33064:15"/>
            <p> I Have done with the Text, a noble Precedent of Piety drawn from the firſt and Golden Age of the world. And now <hi>I</hi> perceive your attention re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vives, and your expectation begins to rouze up, to hear ſomething of the preſent occaſion by way of parallel. And <hi>I</hi> cannot blame you; ſuch eminent Examples of Vertue and Piety, as this Honourable Perſon hath left behind him, are not the lot of every day, eſpecially in this laſt and Iron Age of the world. I ſhall therefore endeavour in ſome meaſure to gratifie ſuch a juſt and reaſonable ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation. And I ſhall doe it the more chearfully, becauſe <hi>I</hi> find my ſelf diſcharg'd of one main diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement which uſually attends upon theſe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formances, the ſuſpicion of Flattery, that Pander of Vain-glory, that <hi>ſtinking Flie</hi> which poiſons the perfume of many a Funeral Commendation. Here is no fear of that, I am to ſpeak of a Perſon ſo truly and highly Deſerving, that my arrows will be ſure rather to fall ſhort then beyond the mark. Being ſecured of that, I ſhall ſet forward.</p>
            <p>I will not take upon me to trace the Deſcent of of this Noble Perſon to its firſt riſe, it were a work that would require the Antiquities of two King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms. It may ſuffice, that it was both Ancient and Honourable; and let me adde, it was <hi>Engliſh</hi> too: and ſo I find it on the Monument of <hi>Edward</hi> Lord <hi>Bruce</hi> in the Chappel of the Rolls,</p>
            <pb n="25" facs="tcp:33064:15"/>
            <p> 
               <hi>Scotus ut ortu, Anglis ſic oriundus avis.</hi> Our neighbour-Nation had the honour to give that Family an hoſpitable entertainment for ſome hundreds of years; and they had the juſtice alſo, after many revolutions, to reſtore it at length with Honour and Splendour to its native and Original Soil.</p>
            <p>His Anceſtors, with their Name, came in with the <hi>Norman</hi> Conquerour, their Seat was <hi>Skelton</hi> in <hi>Yorkſhire;</hi> and a Monument of theirs ſtill remaining in <hi>Gisborough</hi> Abbey bears witneſs to great Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity. Providence tranſplanted them into <hi>Scotland,</hi> where they proſpered, and took root, and ſpread their branches into the Royal Family.</p>
            <p>And the ſame Providence, together with the auſpicious Reign of K. <hi>James,</hi> brought them back into <hi>England.</hi> The L. <hi>Bruce</hi> of <hi>Kinloſſe,</hi> Father to this Honourable Earl, did not onely attend upon his Majeſty to this Crown, but was a happy inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, as Ambaſſadour to Q. <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> (of whoſe favour he had a great ſhare) for the tranſacting of that great Affair, in order to the Succeſſion: and in the Succeſſion, as an honour to his Juſtice and Integrity, as well as Wiſedom and Prudence, was intruſted, both as Maſter of the Rolls in this, and Counſellor of both Kingdoms. Here his own Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſty (which in thoſe days was accounted a Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue) was the onely Moderator which ſet bounds
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:33064:16"/> to the Favour and Bounty of his Prince, in refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing thoſe further offers that were made by K. <hi>James,</hi> and returning divers blanks that had been given unto him.</p>
            <p>His Lordſhip now deceaſed had reaſon to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge (as he did frequently and gratefully) how happy God had made him in all his Relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. Happy in his Father, ſo renowned in his ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration. Happy in his Mother, whoſe Memory is ſtill precious in the fragrancy of her Piety, Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity and Hoſpitality. Happy in his Firſt Wife, the Daughter of Sir <hi>Robert Chicheſter,</hi> and Heir by her Mother to the great and rich Houſe of <hi>Harrington.</hi> By her he had his onely Child, the Earl now living. A Lady eminent in her time for ſingular Wit, Parts and Modeſty. Happy in his Second, <hi>Diana,</hi> Counteſs of <hi>Oxford,</hi> one of the Co-heirs of <hi>William</hi> Earl of <hi>Exceſter;</hi> a Lady of matchleſs Vertue and Honour, to whoſe dear and pious Memory his Lordſhip erected this ſumptuous Monument; having her ſelf left behind her, as with his Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip the memory of a moſt entire Conjugal Affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, ſo with his Son the unparallel'd kindneſs of a Mother-in-law; firſt making him her Child, by a careful Education; and then her Heir, by a noble Endowment with her whole Eſtate of Inheritance. Happy in his onely incomparable Siſter, <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> Counteſs Dowager of <hi>Devonſhire,</hi> now ſurviving.
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:33064:16"/> And happy in his onely Son, and Heir of his Vertues, Fortunes and Honours.</p>
            <p>But I muſt not forget my ſelf, neither ſhould I have mentioned this Nobility of Extraction and Alliance, but that I find it attended with ſuch a train of Vertues, of which Honour is but the ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow, and without which it is not ſo much as a ſhadow. Nobility without Vertue being as a gol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den Candleſtick ſet upon a Table without Light, or as a Beacon upon an hill, having no Fire in it: Whereas Vertue accompanied with Honour is like a rich Diamond ſet in Gold, which makes it appear more orient and illuſtrious. It is a good ſaying of <hi>Gregory Nazianzen,</hi> True Nobility <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, it <hi>is to be meaſured,</hi> not by the Progeny, but <hi>by the Perſon.</hi> Therefore paſſing by his Original and Traduction, let us look upon him in his own pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per and inherent Qualifications. And thoſe we may refer to three heads, Political, Oeconomical, Perſonal.</p>
            <p>For <hi>Politicals,</hi> he was a Perſon enrich'd with great Endowments and Abilities of Mind, much Prudence and Sagacity, as well as Integrity, a deep Judgment fit for the managery of the higheſt Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs, had not the depreſſions and infirmities of a Conſumptive Body indiſpoſed him for the Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick, eſpecially in ſuch Times of Broils and Confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion as were altogether unſutable to the Calmneſs
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:33064:17"/> and Peaceableneſs of his temper. Yet even then he bore his part, and whilſt others were wallowing in bloud, he was wreſtling in Prayer and melting in Tears, <hi>mourning for the Diviſions of Reuben,</hi> and <hi>pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for the peace of Jeruſalem.</hi> And we muſt all con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs that the Prayers of ſuch Good men were ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectual to retrive thoſe publick Bleſſings of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, Peace and Liberty, which the dint of the Sword could never doe. For his own Concernment, his greateſt care was to preſerve <hi>bonam Conſcientiam in mala valetudine, a ſound Soul in a crazie Body,</hi> and a good Conſcience in bad Times. He would often comfort himſelf, and this comfort he carried with him to his grave, that <hi>He was free from the bloud of all men.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For his <hi>Oeconomicals,</hi> in the government of his Domeſtick affairs, his Family was, as the Pſalmiſt deſcribes <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> like <hi>a City compact together.</hi> In the midſt of the diſtracted and confuſed Times, when the Coat of Chriſt was rent into ſo many pieces, ſo many men, almoſt ſo many ſeveral Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligions; in the midſt of thoſe Confuſions, his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily was like a little Church; and though at that time very numerous, yet I could not obſerve that there were two amongſt them all of a different Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſion, either in point of Religion or Loyalty. This I aſcribe (next to the Bleſſing of God, who <hi>makes men to be of one mind in a houſe)</hi> to the Piety and
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:33064:17"/> Prudence of their Lord and Maſter, wiſely conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that he could never be ill ſerved by thoſe, who were both Religious Servants of God, and Faithful Subjects to their Sovereign. Within thoſe Walls you ſhould not hear any of thoſe helliſh Oaths, Blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies or Execrations, which in other places are wont to infect the air, and grate the ears, and wound the hearts of pious men. No Drunkenneſs or Debauche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to be found there. I obſerv'd it with comfort, and can ſpeak it with confidence, that for five years time, in which I had the honour of a conſtant attendance in the ſervice of that Noble Family, I was not once encountred with the deformed ſpectacle of a Drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken diſtemper; but on the contrary, ſuch Order, Silence, Sobriety, Modeſty and Civility, as if not onely the Eye, but the Soul of the Maſter had been in every corner of the houſe. Such a Maſter worthy of ſuch a Family, who was truly <hi>Pater-familiâs,</hi> not ſo much the Lord, as <hi>Father of his Family;</hi> ſo tender of his Servants whilſt living, and ſo careful of them when dying, as to leave to every of them a good bleſſing behind him.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, for his own <hi>Perſonal</hi> qualifications, he was moſt eminent and exemplary. I ſhall not inſtance in any Negative Vertues, that he was not obnoxious to any of thoſe Vices which are incident to Greatneſs, not to Pride and haughtineſs, not to Violence and oppreſſion, not to Luxury and intemperance, not to
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:33064:18"/> Pleaſure and wantonneſs: the black mouth of malice cannot charge him with any ſhadow of theſe Enor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities. But I will not inſiſt upon theſe. <hi>Privati &amp; ple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beii hominis eſt, ut vitio careat,</hi> as <hi>Nazianzen</hi> ſpeaks, <hi>It may be the commendation of a Plebeian,</hi> or <hi>Private man, to be free from Vice;</hi> but for Perſons that overtop others in place and Dignity, it is a ſhameful and ignominious thing not to be as eminent above them in Vertue. And what Vertue can we name, in which he did not both tranſcend the moſt, and equalize the beſt?</p>
            <p>Begin we with his <hi>Humility,</hi> for that's the beſt foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation in the ſtructure of Piety. He that would build high, muſt lay his foundation low; and he that would build for Heaven, muſt lay his foundation in Humility.</p>
            <p>So did he, great in the eyes of others, little onely in his own. And whereas <hi>Solomon</hi> tells us, <hi>Before ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour goes humility;</hi> here was Humility conſpicuous in <note place="margin">Pro. 15. 33</note> the midſt of Honour, which made it appear much more honourable. Like <hi>Saul</hi> in the Old Teſtament, he was <hi>higher then the reſt of the people by the head and ſhoulders;</hi> yet like <hi>Paul</hi> in the New Teſtament, in his own eſteem <hi>leſs then the leaſt.</hi> His grandeur diſcover'd it ſelf rather by the virtue and influence in <hi>doing good,</hi> then by the pomp and ſplendour in <hi>ſeeming great.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Adde to his Humility his exceeding virginal <hi>Mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty,</hi> mix'd with ſuch a ſober and ſerious Gravity in his countenance and deportment, that his very Preſence
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:33064:18"/> was ſufficient to charm the extravagancie of wanton tongues, as wel as his Example. You ſhould not hear at any time an unſavoury word fall from his mouth. He had ſuch a perfect command of that little ſlippery member, that whereas others, to whom their own Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour is tender as the apple of their eye, are yet unrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonably prodigal of other mens Reputations; he was ſo far from lacerating the fame of other men, that I could never obſerve him to ſpeak ill of any man's perſon, though never ſo ill deſerving.</p>
            <p>His <hi>Temperance</hi> was rare and admirable: he look'd upon Exceſs as poiſon, not onely of the body, but of the better part, and ſuch a baſtard of Hoſpitality, as moſt commonly is the death of the mother.</p>
            <p>His <hi>Juſtice</hi> exact, ſo far from doing wrong to others, that if the caſe were doubtful, he would commonly take the loſs and diſadvantage to himſelf.</p>
            <p>But <hi>above all theſe,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>put on Charity.</hi> So did he: his <hi>Charity</hi> was great; both this and the other adjacent Pariſhes had a conſtant and a liberal portion of it. But beſides the ordinary and obvious ways, he had the art to ſpie out the more choice and noble objects of Bounty, (of which the late unhappy Times afforded plenty) and there he ſowed plenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully, by many hundreds in the year. And this he did in ſuch a ſecret manner, that none could be witneſſes but God himſelf, and thoſe to whom he gave it for God's cauſe. And though he always gave it with his
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:33064:19"/> own hand, that he might be ſure to give it into right hands; yet he was unwilling that his <hi>left hand</hi> ſhould <hi>know what his right had done.</hi> And whereas <hi>Charity covers a multitude of ſins,</hi> his Charity was ſo modeſt as to cover it ſelf.</p>
            <p>Theſe were the Fruits of a conſtant courſe of Piety and Devotion, which he did moſt religiouſly ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve both in publick and private.</p>
            <p>In the time of his Sickneſs, which was long, and accompanied often with ſharp pains, he wanted not a large ſtock of Patience and Chriſtian Fortitude, to comply with that gracious Providence which had put the Cup into his hand. But having a clear pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of <hi>the race which was ſet before him,</hi> by daily Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tification, and Prayer, and other exerciſes of Piety, he carefully prepared for his laſt and great <hi>Change,</hi> which befell him in the great Climacterical year of his life, meekly reſigning his Soul into the hands of his Gracious Redeemer.</p>
            <p>It remains on our part, to commit his remaining Part, as a ſacred <hi>Depoſitum,</hi> to that Dormitory which himſelf prepared, beſeeching God to give us Grace to tread in the ſteps of ſuch Pious Examples, that when our own <hi>Change ſhall come,</hi> our Souls may be received into the ſame bleſſed Manſions, and at the general Reſurrection we together with them may have the ſame conſummation of Bliſs both in Soul and Body; through <hi>Jeſus</hi> Chriſt our Lord.</p>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:33064:19"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
